Guide to the Collins Land Company (Helena, Mont.) Records 1898-1951
Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, The University of Montana--Missoula
- Case Files, 1907-1951; Series II; 28.5 linear feet
  - Sequence 3, Subseries 3; 11.5 linear feet
    - Bassett, J. D., Ritzville, Washington, Case Number 1082 (Box-folder 67/12)
    - Big Sky Land and Livestock Company, Great Falls, Montana, Case Number 1083 (Box-folder 67/13)
    - Daly, Charles, Miles City, Montana, Case Number 1084 (Box-folder 67/14)
    - Cook-Reynolds Company, Lewistown, Montana, Case Number 1085 (Box-folder 67/15)
    - Newhall, E. B., Big Sandy, Montana, Case Number 1089 (Box-folder 67/16)
    - Guerry, Hower, Washington, D.C., Case Number 1090 (Box-folder 67/17)
    - Mach, R. W., Big Sandy, Montana, Case Number 1092 (Box-folder 67/18)
    - Fogarty, Edward, Sand Cliffs, Montana, Case Number 1094 (Box-folder 68/1)
    - Hill, H. B., Mondak, Montana, Case Number 1095 (Box-folder 68/2)
    - Ramsland, T. P., Lemon, South Dakota, Case Number 1097 (Box-folder 68/3)
    - Fray, W. S., Great Falls, Montana, Case Number 1099 (Box-folder 68/4)
    - Cowell, Alvin J., Choteau, Montana, Case Number 1100 (Box-folder 68/5)
    - Western Lumber Company, Missoula, Montana, Case Number 1102 (Box-folder 68/6)
    - McBride, Alexander, Culbertson, Montana, Case Number 1103 (Box-folder 68/7)
    - Osnes, Ole G., Knerville, Montana, Case Number 1104 (Box-folder 68/8)
    - Washington Office, Case Number 1106 (Box-folder 68/9)
    - Riba, Adolph, Plentywood, Montana, Case Number 1107 (Box-folder 68/10)
    - Woodward, L. A., Sundance, Wyoming, Case Number 1108 (Box-folder 68/11)
    - Mills, Jacob, Helena, Montana, Case Number 1110 (Box-folder 68/12)
    - Hilger Loan and Realty Company, Lewistown, Montana, Case Number 1111 (Box-folder 68/13)
    - Nystad, Jens F., Shelby, Montana, Case Number 1116 (Box-folder 68/14)
    - Hartt, Dudley N., Two Dot, Montana, Case Number 1118 (Box-folder 68/15)
    - Bain, Charles N., Bainville, Montana, Case Number 1119 (Box-folder 68/16)
    - Fogarty, Jennie A., Sand Cliffs, Montana, Case Number 1121 (Box-folder 68/17)
    - Prescott, A. K., Helena, Montana, Case Number 1122 (Box-folder 68/18)
    - Wheeler, A. E., Great Falls, Montana, Case Number 1127 (Box-folder 68/19)
    - Redwater Land and Livestock Company, Helena, Montana, Case Number 1128 (Box-folder 68/20)
    - Downing, W. G., Great Falls, Montana, Case Number 1129 (Box-folder 68/21)
    - Fogarty, Jennie A., Sand Cliffs, Montana, Case Number 1130 (Box-folder 68/22)
    - Cage, Milton C., Boise, Idaho, Case Number 1132 (Box-folder 68/23)
    - Hixden, Lewis E., Hilger Loan and Realty Company, Lewistown, Montana, Case Number 1134 (Box-folder 69/1)
    - Jackson, Peter V., Norris, Montana, Case Number 1135 (Box-folder 69/2)
    - Fitzpatrick, John E., Sweet Grass, Montana, Case Number 1136 (Box-folder 69/3)
    - Wheeler, A. E., Great Falls, Montana, Case Number 1137 (Box-folder 69/4)
    - Swank, Wesley T., Nashua, Montana, Case Number 1138 (Box-folder 69/5)
    - Stilwell, James, Fort Benton, Montana, Case Number 1139 (Box-folder 69/6)
    - Coulter, G. H. Culbertson, Montana, Case Number 1140 (Box-folder 69/7)
    - Van Camp, Alfred, Martinsdale, Montana, Case Number 1141 (Box-folder 69/8)
    - Hilger, David, Lewistown, Montana, Case Number 1142 (Box-folder 69/9)
    - Rhoades, J. M., Missoula, Montana, Case Number 1144 (Box-folder 69/10)
    - Kingsbury, A. W., Great Falls, Montana, Case Number 1145 (Box-folder 69/11)
    - Milner, M. E., Fort Benton, Montana, Case Number 1146 (Box-folder 69/12)
    - Hilger and Busenburg, Lewistown, Montana, Case Number 1148 (Box-folder 69/13)
    - Abrams, James A., Polaris, Montana, Case Number 1149 (Box-folder 69/14)
    - Kendrick, John B., Sheridan, Wyoming, Case Number 1151 (Box-folder 69/15)
    - McGirl, Thomas, Billings, Montana, Case Number 1153 (Box-folder 69/16)
    - Kerr, John S., Camp Crook, South Dakota, Case Number 1154 (Box-folder 69/17)
    - Power, Thomas C., Helena, Montana, Case Number 1155 (Box-folder 69/18)
    - Carver, Mary D., Red Rock, Montana, Case Number 1156 (Box-folder 69/19)
    - Conrad Investment Company, Great Falls, Montana, Case Number 1157 (Box-folder 69/20)
    - Van Camp, Alfred, Martinsdale, Montana, Case Number 1158 (Box-folder 69/21)
    - Sullivan, Daniel J., Shelby, Montana, Case Number 1160 (Box-folder 69/22)
    - Bassett, J. D., Ritzville, Washington, Case Number 1162 (Box-folder 69/23)
    - Wade, John W., Helena, Montana, Case Number 1164 (Box-folder 69/24)
    - Day, J. S., Culbertson, Montana, Case Number 1166 (Box-folder 69/25)
    - Evans, H. R., Malad City, Idaho, Case Number 1167 (Box-folder 69/26)
    - Stevenson, B. R., Wisdom, Montana, Case Number 1168 (Box-folder 70/1)
    - Harris, C. L., Billings, Montana, Case Number 1170 (Box-folder 70/2)
    - Winnecook Land and Livestock Company, Helena, Montana, Case Number 1171 (Box-folder 70/3)
    - Osnes, Ole G., Knerville, Montana, Case Number 1172 (Box-folder 70/4)
    - Poindexter, J. B., Dillon, Montana, Case Number 1173 (Box-folder 70/5)
    - Ellis, Edward W., Millegan, Montana, Case Number 1174 (Box-folder 70/6)
    - Johnson, Andrew, Melville, Montana, Case Number 1175 (Box-folder 70/7)
    - Metz, Sackett and Metz, Sheridan, Wyoming, Case Number 1176 (Box-folder 70/8)
    - Biddle, S. F. B., Gillette, Wyoming, Case Number 1177 (Box-folder 70/9)
    - Smith Brothers Sheep Company, Martinsdale, Montana, Case Number 1178 (Box-folder 70/10)
    - Prescott, Alonzo K., Helena, Montana, Case Number 1180 (Box-folder 70/11)
    - Skillman, C. N., Big Timber, Montana, Case Number 1181 (Box-folder 70/12)
    - Sprague, Robert H., Lyon, Montana, Case Number 1183 (Box-folder 70/13)
    - Northwestern Lumber Company, Kalispell, Montana, Case Number 1185 (Box-folder 70/14)
    - Moss, Preston B., Billings, Montana, Case Number 1186 (Box-folder 70/15)
    - Landon, Frank, Dillon, Montana, Case Number 1187 (Box-folder 70/16)
    - Melum, B. M., Capitol, Montana, Case Number 1188 (Box-folder 70/17)
    - Oleson, Christopher, Capitol, Montana, Case Number 1190 (Box-folder 70/18)
    - Maczek, Andro, Stockett, Montana, Case Number 1191 (Box-folder 70/19)
    - Hughes, McMicken, Dovell and Ramsey, Seattle, Washington, Case Number 1192 (Box-folder 70/20)
    - Johnson, A. S., Dillon, Montana, Case Number 1193 (Box-folder 71/1)
    - Biggs, W. M., Helena, Montana, Case Number 1194 (Box-folder 71/2)
    - Price, L. J., Dillon, Montana, Case Number 1195 (Box-folder 71/3)
    - Blair, Joseph M., Helmville, Montana, Case Number 1196 (Box-folder 71/4)
    - Miracle, Frank D., Helena, Montana, Case Number 1197 (Box-folder 71/5)
    - Bruckert, Mrs. Albert, Jr., White Sulphur Springs, Montana, Case Number 1198 (Box-folder 71/6)
    - Gibson and Carpenter, Glasgow, Montana, Case Number 1199 (Box-folder 71/7)
    - First National Bank, Rock Springs, Wyoming, Case Number 1200 (Box-folder 71/8)
    - Mathews, W., Culbertson, Montana, Case Number 1202 (Box-folder 71/9)
    - Hill, H. B., Mondak, Montana, Case Number 1203 (Box-folder 71/10)
    - C. E. Shoemaker and Company, Lewistown, Montana, Case Number 1204 (Box-folder 71/11)
    - Bonnes, Joseph, Poplar, Montana, Case Number 1205 (Box-folder 71/12)
    - Yegen Brothers, Billings, Montana, Case Number 1206 (Box-folder 71/13)
    - Calvin Investment Company, Miles City, Montana, Case Number 1207 (Box-folder 71/14)
    - Darling, M. S., Conrad, Montana, Case Number 1208 (Box-folder 71/15)
    - Prescott, A. K., Helena, Montana, Case Number 1210 (Box-folder 71/16)
    - First National Bank, Culbertson, Montana, Case Number 1212 (Box-folder 71/17)
    - Arnott, John P., Basin, Wyoming, Case Number 1213 (Box-folder 71/18)
    - Eccles, Robert, Gillette, Wyoming, Case Number 1214 (Box-folder 71/19)
    - Helena Power and Transmission Company, Helena, Montana, Case Number 1215 (Box-folder 72/1)
    - Benbrooks, W. T., Meeteetse, Wyoming, Case Number 1217 (Box-folder 72/2)
    - Helena Power and Transmission Company, Helena, Montana, Case Number 1218 (Box-folder 72/3)
    - Suiste, Minnie J., Pendleton, Oregon, Case Number 1220 (Box-folder 72/4)
    - Neill, John S. M., Helena, Montana, Case Number 1221 (Box-folder 72/5)
    - Wilson, Frederick, Malta, Montana, Case Number 1223 (Box-folder 72/6)
    - Bear Tooth Livestock Company, Craig, Montana, Case Number 1224 (Box-folder 72/7)
    - Price, L. J., Dillon, Montana, Case Number 1226 (Box-folder 72/8)
    - Moen, Ole and Brack, Sivert M., Melville, Montana, Case Number 1227 (Box-folder 72/9)
    - Big Sag Land and Livestock Company, Great Falls, Montana, Case Number 1229 (Box-folder 72/10)
    - Murphy, John T., Helena, Montana, Case Number 1230 (Box-folder 72/11)
    - Jackson, Peter V., Norris, Montana, Case Number 1233 (Box-folder 72/12)
    - Hampton, D. Ewing, Basin, Wyoming, Case Number 1237 (Box-folder 72/13)
    - Cannon, Henry, Adel, Montana, Case Number 1240 (Box-folder 72/14)
    - Phosphate Lands, Case Number 1242 (Box-folder 72/15)
    - Steele, James B., Three Creek, Idaho, Case Number 1243 (Box-folder 72/16)
    - Montague, George W., Arlington, Oregon, Case Number 1245 (Box-folder 72/17)
    - Smith, William, Arlington, Oregon, Case Number 1246 (Box-folder 72/18)
    - Jackson, J. W., Goldendale, Washington, Case Number 1247 (Box-folder 72/19)
    - Jordan, Charles G., Brickleton, Washington, Case Number 1248 (Box-folder 72/20)
    - Osnes, Ole G., Knerville, Montana, Case Number 1249 (Box-folder 73/1)
    - Osnes, Ole G., Knerville, Montana, Case Number 1250 (Box-folder 73/2)
    - Eie, Peder J., Knerville, Montana, Case Number 1253 (Box-folder 73/3)
    - Boyle, Charles H., Fort Benton, Montana, Case Number 1256 (Box-folder 73/4)
    - Davenport, Don, Helena, Montana, Case Number 1257 (Box-folder 73/5)
    - Phillips, B. D., Phillips, Montana, Case Number 1259 (Box-folder 73/6)
    - Neild, William D., Townsend, Montana, Case Number 1262 (Box-folder 73/7)
    - Milner, M. E., Fort Benton, Montana, Case Number 1263 (Box-folder 73/8)
    - Pioneer Cattle Company, Helena, Montana, Case Number 1264 (Box-folder 73/9)
    - Judith Mercantile and Cattle Company, Helena, Montana, Case Number 1265 (Box-folder 73/10)
  - Sequence 4, Subseries 4; 0.5 linear feet
    - Leary, Wilson T., Kalispell, Montana, Case Number 0 (Box-folder 74/1)
    - Winans, W. P., Walla Walla, Montana, Case Number 2 (Box-folder 74/2)
    - Flower, Charles E., Brickleton, Washington, Case Number 4 (Box-folder 74/3)
    - Woody and Burbank, Spokane, Washington, Case Number 5 (Box-folder 74/4)
    - Smythe, A., Arlington, Oregon, Case Number 6 (Box-folder 74/5)
    - Dove, G. A., Brickleton, Washington, Case Number 7 (Box-folder 74/6)
    - Richardson, Mrs. T. B., Arlington, Oregon, Case Number 8 (Box-folder 74/7)
    - Wheelhouse, Lillian E., Arlington, Oregon, Case Number 12 (Box-folder 74/8)
    - Swanson, Nils, Ione, Oregon, Case Number 13 (Box-folder 74/9)
    - Swanson, Nils, Ione, Oregon, Case Number 14 (Box-folder 74/10)
    - McKinney, Washington M., Blalock, Oregon, Case Number 16 (Box-folder 74/11)
    - Everett, Louie N., Lento, Oregon, Case Number 22 (Box-folder 74/12)
    - Glock, Edward, Ione, Oregon, Case Number 26 (Box-folder 74/13)
    - Glock, Edward, Ione, Oregon, Case Number 27 (Box-folder 74/14)
    - Glock, Edward, Ione, Oregon, Case Number 28 (Box-folder 74/15)
    - Glock, Lizzie, Ione, Oregon, Case Number 29 (Box-folder 74/16)
    - Thomas, W. A., Cecil, Oregon, Case Number 30 (Box-folder 74/17)
    - Schroeder, August H., Goldendale, Virginia, Case Number 31 (Box-folder 74/18)
    - MacGillivray, J. K., Salt Lake City, Utah, Case Number 33 (Box-folder 74/19)
    - Slusher, W. M., Pendleton, Oregon, Case Number 36 (Box-folder 74/20)
    - Slusher, W. M., Pendleton, Oregon, Case Number 37 (Box-folder 74/21)
    - Fix, Charles J., Pendleton, Oregon, Case Number 42 (Box-folder 74/22)
    - Fix, Monrod M., Pendleton, Oregon, Case Number 46 (Box-folder 74/23)
- Legal and Financial, 1900-1921; Series III; 1.5 linear feet and 2 oversize volumes
  This series contains one folder of financial records, 10 bound financial volumes, and one folder of legal documents generated by the Collins Land Company, including two volumes tracking account activity for land scrips allotted to Union Civil War veterans and soldiers who fought in the Spanish-American War. Legal documents include property deeds, prospecting patents, and court transcripts.
  - Financial Records, 1904-1905 and undated (Box-folder 75/1)
  - Legal Documents, 1900-1921 (Box-folder 75/2)
  - Journal, August 1911-June 1915 (Box-volume 75/1)
  - Journal, June 1915-December 1917 (Box-volume 75/2)
  - Journal, December 1917-December 1920 (Volume 3)
  - Ledger, September 1898-August 1901 (Box-volume 76/4)
  - Ledger, September 1905-December 1911 (Volume 5)
  - Cash Book, May 1917-December 1920 (Box-volume 76/6)
  - Ledger, Washington Office, 1901 (Box-volume 76/7)
  - Journal, Washington Office, December 1911-December 1917 (Box-volume 77/8)
  - Soldier's Additional Purchases, #2, 1909-1915 (Box-volume 77/9)
  - Soldier's Additional Purchases, Index to #2, 1900-1912 (Box-volume 77/10)
- Printed Materials, 1899-1951; Series IV; 1.0 linear feet
  This series contains Collins Land Company publications and advertisements as well as an extensive sequence of Federal government publications relating to management and dissolution of public lands. These government publications include Congressional legislation and U.S. Department of the Interior regulations.
  - Collins Land Company Publications and Advertisements, 1900-1933 (Box-folder 77/1)
  - Government Publications, 1899-1921 (Box-folder 77/2)
  - Government Publications, 1902-1921 (Box-folder 78/1)
  - Government Publications, 1909-1921 (Box-folder 78/2)
  - Government Publications, 1912-1921 (Box-folder 78/3)
  - Government Publications, 1912-1921 (Box-folder 78/4)
  - Government Publications, 1912-1921 (Box-folder 78/5)
  - Government Publications, 1912-1921 (Box-folder 78/6)
  - Government Publications, 1912-1921 (Box-folder 78/7)
  - Government Publications, 1912-1921 (Box-folder 79/1)
  - Government Publications, 1912-1921 (Box-folder 79/2)
  - Government Publications, 1912-1921 (Box-folder 79/3)
  - Government Publications, 1922-1951 (Box-folder 79/4)
  - Government Publications, 1935-1941 (Box-folder 79/5)
- Organization, 1899-1919; Series V; 0.25 linear feet
  This series consists of one bound volume containing the Collins Land Company's corporate bylaws and stockholder meeting minutes.
  - Bylaws, 1899 (Box-volume 79/11)
  - Minutes, 1899-1919 (Box-volume 79/11)
- Collins Realty Company, 1909-1920; Series VI; 0.5 linear feet and 1 oversize volume
  This series contains four bound volumes of financial journals generated by the Collins Realty Company, a real estate development business headquartered in Helena, Montana.
  - Journal, April 1909-February 1915 (Box-volume 80/12)
  - Journal, February 1915-April 1918 (Box-volume 80/13)
  - Journal, April 1918-July 1920 (Box-volume 80/14)
  - Journal, July 1920-December 1920 (Volume 15)
- Collins Company, 1906-1920; Series VII; 0.25 linear feet
  This series contains a daily transaction ledger generated by the Collins Company, a holding company for Collins family business interests and located in Helena, Montana.
  - Day Book, January 1906-December 1920 (Box-volume 81/16)
- Beartooth Stock Company, 1912-1939; Series VIII; 0.25 linear feet
  This series consists of one bound volume containing the Beartooth Stock Company's articles of incorporation and stockholder meeting minutes. The company was a livestock raising and agricultural development business headquartered in Helena, Montana.
  - Articles of Incorporation, September 1912 (Box-volume 81/17)
  - Minutes, October 1912-January 1939 (Box-volume 81/17)